<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://defundclimatechaos.uk/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://defundclimatechaos.uk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-10-13T14:34:27+01:00</updated><id>https://defundclimatechaos.uk/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Defund Climate Chaos</title><subtitle>UK banks, investors and insurers are pumping billions of pounds into fossil
fuels that worsen the climate crisis.

On October 29th, ahead of UN climate talks, groups around the world and
UK are rising up to demand that the UK government and corporations
#DefundClimateChaos.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Protest Outside First Ever Barclays Bank</title><link href="https://defundclimatechaos.uk/stories/By-XR-Buddhists/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Protest Outside First Ever Barclays Bank" /><published>2021-09-17T15:04:56+01:00</published><updated>2021-09-17T15:04:56+01:00</updated><id>https://defundclimatechaos.uk/stories/By%20XR%20Buddhists</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://defundclimatechaos.uk/stories/By-XR-Buddhists/">&lt;p&gt;By Extinction Rebellion Buddhists&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite its stated commitment to &lt;a href=&quot;https://home.barclays/society/our-position-on-climate-change/&quot;&gt;reduce its lending to move to net zero emissions by 2050&lt;/a&gt;, Barclays has actually &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cityam.com/barclays-fossil-fuel-financing-increases-despite-net-zero-pledge/&quot;&gt;increased their lending to fossil fuels projects last year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barclays has invested almost&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ran.org/bankingonclimatechaos2021/&quot;&gt; $145bn in fossil fuel industries since the Paris Agreement&lt;/a&gt; on Climate Change in 2015. Barclays is the biggest investor in fossil fuel projects of any bank in Europe and seventh biggest in the world. The bank’s investments are also impacting indigenous communities in the USA and elsewhere, and increasing deforestation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why Extinction Rebellion Buddhists UK conducted a walking meditation to the beat of a slow drum to Barclays Bank at 19 Fleet Street, the first Barclays to be opened in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/fullsizeoutput_64de-1536x1276.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a lovely building, but unfortunately the history of its investments is not so lovely. From its funding of the apartheid regime in the 1960s, to its current continuing funding of destructive coal, oil and gas projects across the planet, it continues to be a destructive force in the financial world. And this is despite the clear scientific evidence of the imminent dangers of its investments and its pledge to be a net-zero bank by 2050. XR Buddhists are engaging in a peaceful meditation action today. In bringing our faith tradition to the front lines of activism, we embody a peaceful determination to protect our one precious Earth and all of life. We hold the staff of Barclays in our hearts also; they are also going to be impacted by climate breakdown. But as a company, we consider Barclays to be acting in a way that meets the definition of the crime of ecocide, recently published by the Ecocide Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crime of Ecocide has been formulated by an independent expert panel comprising twelve lawyers from around the world. They are proposing that the crime of  Ecocide be added to the Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court. This would make it a criminal offence to commit: unlawful or wanton acts committed with knowledge that there is a substantial likelihood of severe and either widespread or long-term damage to the environment being caused by those acts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are almost a quarter of a million Buddhists in the UK: a growing number are becoming concerned about the impacts that humans are having on the climate and on other living beings.  Recently, the Dalai Lama joined &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buddhistdoor.net/news/dalai-lama-joins-nobel-laureates-in-earth-day-appeal-to-eliminate-fossil-fuels&quot;&gt;100 other Nobel Prize laureates to call for action on climate change&lt;/a&gt;.  The letter stated “Climate change is threatening hundreds of millions of lives, livelihoods across every continent, and is putting thousands of species at risk. The burning of fossil fuels—coal, oil, and gas—is by far the major contributor to climate change”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://defundclimatechaos.uk/#map&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;» Join an action near your or organise you own on the 29th Oct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">By Extinction Rebellion Buddhists</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://defundclimatechaos.uk/assets/images/signal-2021-09-12-191857_001.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://defundclimatechaos.uk/assets/images/signal-2021-09-12-191857_001.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Why central banks should be a target for the climate movement</title><link href="https://defundclimatechaos.uk/stories/By-Positive-Money/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why central banks should be a target for the climate movement" /><published>2021-09-17T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-09-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://defundclimatechaos.uk/stories/By%20Positive%20Money</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://defundclimatechaos.uk/stories/By-Positive-Money/">&lt;p&gt;By Positive Money&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 2016, the year that global leaders committed to “&lt;a href=&quot;https://unfccc.int/files/meetings/paris_nov_2015/application/pdf/paris_agreement_english_.pdf&quot;&gt;making financial flows consistent with a pathway towards low greenhouse gas emissions&lt;/a&gt;”, the world’s 60 largest commercial and investment banks have funnelled an aggregate of&lt;a href=&quot;http://priceofoil.org/content/uploads/2021/04/Banking_On_Climate_Chaos_2021_vF.pdf&quot;&gt; $3.8 trillion &lt;/a&gt;into fossil fuels. To put this number into context, if the UK’s financial institutions were a country, they would have the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.greenpeace.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2021/05/The-Big-Smoke-the-global-emissions-of-the-UK-financial-sector.pdf&quot;&gt;9th largest emissions in the world&lt;/a&gt;; ahead of both Germany and Canada’s domestic emissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That financial institutions are breaking their promises should not come as a surprise. Within a system in which profit is the raison d’être, banks will continue to fund &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/science-environment-58130705&quot;&gt;climate and ecological collapse&lt;/a&gt; until their rules and incentives are changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Central banks influence the flow of money in our economy by deciding where and how it is injected into the financial system. By &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lse.ac.uk/granthaminstitute/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/ClimateImpactQuantEasing_Matikainen-et-al.pdf&quot;&gt;purchasing fossil fuel assets &lt;/a&gt;and &lt;a href=&quot;https://neweconomics.org/uploads/files/Collateral-Framework.pdf&quot;&gt;accepting them as ‘collateral’&lt;/a&gt; in exchange for loans, central banks prop up the value of these assets, ultimately making them more desirable. In their capacity as regulators of banks, insurance firms, and financial corporations, central banks and financial supervisors tempt both&lt;a href=&quot;https://thehill.com/policy/equilibrium-sustainability/572229-banks-at-bigger-risk-from-climate-than-subprime-mortgages&quot;&gt; financial crash and climate collapse&lt;/a&gt; when they fail to account for climate risk while setting the rules of the financial system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this can, and must, change. Price, financial, and climate stability are all fundamentally interdependent. Until central banks actively steer private finance in line with the net-zero transition, they are jeopardising both the fulfilment of their core objectives, price and financial stability, and their secondary objective to support government policy. Increasingly, central banks’ remits are being &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bankofengland.co.uk/-/media/boe/files/letter/2021/march/2021-mpc-remit-letter.pdf?la=en&quot;&gt;updated &lt;/a&gt;to explicitly include net-zero and environmental sustainability. In all cases, therefore, central banks have a duty to protect the environment from finance and vice versa. This should involve excluding fossil fuels assets from their &lt;a href=&quot;https://neweconomics.org/uploads/files/NEF-Decarbonise-BoE-report.pdf&quot;&gt;own operations&lt;/a&gt;, requiring&lt;a href=&quot;https://neweconomics.org/2021/06/greening-finance-to-build-back-better&quot;&gt; mandatory transition plans&lt;/a&gt; for financial institutions, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.finance-watch.org/publication/breaking-the-climate-finance-doom-loop/&quot;&gt;introducing rules&lt;/a&gt; that require banks to hold more capital against fossil fuel loans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond steering private finance, it is high time for central banks to work with governments to ensure that the transition to a zero carbon economy is just for industry workers and those on low incomes. Central banks must urgently use their money creation powers to scale up public investment into green industries. For example, they could help &lt;a href=&quot;https://positivemoney.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/Greening-finance-for-a-BBB-recovery-FINAL-2.pdf&quot;&gt;capitalise&lt;/a&gt; (or &lt;a href=&quot;https://greencentralbanking.com/2021/07/07/central-bank-independence-myth/&quot;&gt;purchase bonds&lt;/a&gt; issued by) green public investment banks, coordinate with finance departments to keep&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/bartlett/public-purpose/sites/public-purpose/files/iipp-wp-2018-08.pdf&quot;&gt; government borrowing costs low&lt;/a&gt;, or more&lt;a href=&quot;https://positivemoney.org/2020/04/major-breakthrough-on-public-money-creation-the-bank-of-england-will-directly-finance-government-coronavirus-spending/&quot;&gt; directly finance&lt;/a&gt; green government spending. Given that central banks across the world engaged in various forms of coordination with governments in&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bankofengland.co.uk/markets/covid-corporate-financing-facility&quot;&gt; response to COVID-19,&lt;/a&gt; and indeed at various times throughout history, there is no reason they can’t do so to build a green economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/1-4-21_no_more_fossil_fools_bank_of_englandwilliam_joshua_templeton_photographer-8.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The climate movement has already put climate change on the agenda of central banks. Largely thanks to public campaigning, more than 80 central banks have joined the Network for Greening the Financial System, a coalition working to decarbonise finance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking ahead to COP26 central banks must not be judged by their words but their actions. In the Positive Money&lt;a href=&quot;http://positivemoney.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/Positive-Money-Green-Central-Banking-Scorecard-Report-31-Mar-2021-Single-Pages.pdf&quot;&gt; Green Central Bank Scorecard&lt;/a&gt;, although 13 G20 countries scored full marks in their Research and Advocacy policies, not a single country has implemented a high impact policy. If activists seek to stop money being funnelled into the most polluting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://defundclimatechaos.uk/actions/national-climate-justice-memorial-0/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Join us for the National Climate Justice Memorial from 5.30pm on Friday 29th Oct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">By Positive Money</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://defundclimatechaos.uk/assets/images/1-4-21_no_more_fossil_fools_bank_of_englandwilliam_joshua_templeton_photographer-8.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://defundclimatechaos.uk/assets/images/1-4-21_no_more_fossil_fools_bank_of_englandwilliam_joshua_templeton_photographer-8.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>